<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Code on Matthew Leonawicz | Blog: I think, therefore I R</title>
    <link>/tags/code/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Code on Matthew Leonawicz | Blog: I think, therefore I R</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Matthew Leonawicz</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/code/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>My 2018 #rstats year in review</title>
      <link>/post/my-2018-rstats-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/my-2018-rstats-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>This past year in R has been a good one for me; productive, exciting, different. I decided it was worth taking a moment to reflect and share. Goals were set and met. There were also unexpected changes.
CRANA year ago, at the tail end of 2017, I published my first package to CRAN. It’s a fun, silly package, but I also had to make a successful case for in the initial review process to distinguish it from other similar works.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>epubr 0.5.0 CRAN release</title>
      <link>/post/epubr-0-5-0-cran-release/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/epubr-0-5-0-cran-release/</guid>
      <description>The epubr package provides functions supporting the reading and parsing of internal e-book content from EPUB files. This post briefly highlights the changes from v0.4.0. See the vignette for a more comprehensive introduction.
Minor additionThere is not much to see with the upgrade to version 0.5.0. Only one user function has been added, epub_cat. All this does is allow you to cat chunks of parsed e-book text to the console in a more readable manner.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>tiler 0.2.0 CRAN release: Create map tiles from R</title>
      <link>/post/tiler-0-2-0-cran-release-create-map-tiles-from-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tiler-0-2-0-cran-release-create-map-tiles-from-r/</guid>
      <description>The tiler package provides a map tile-generator function for creating map tile sets for use with packages such as leaflet.
In addition to generating map tiles based on a common raster layer source, it also handles the non-geographic edge case, producing map tiles from arbitrary images. These map tiles, which have a “simple CRS”, a non-geographic simple Cartesian coordinate reference system, can also be used with leaflet when applying the simple CRS option.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>epubr 0.4.0 CRAN release</title>
      <link>/post/epubr-0-4-0-cran-release/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/epubr-0-4-0-cran-release/</guid>
      <description>The epubr package provides functions supporting the reading and parsing of internal e-book content from EPUB files. E-book metadata and text content are parsed separately and joined together in a tidy, nested tibble data frame.
E-book formatting is non-standard enough across all literature that no function can curate parsed e-book content across an arbitrary collection of e-books, in completely general form, resulting in a singular, consistently formatted output containing all the same variables.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>mapmate 0.2.0</title>
      <link>/post/mapmate-0-2-0/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/mapmate-0-2-0/</guid>
      <description>mapmate is under development and blog posts can become outdated quickly. Up to date mapmate documentation and tutorial examples can be found at the official mapmate Github pages.
mapmate has now been updating from version 0.1.0 to 0.2.0 on Github. The key change is the incorporation of new functions, help docs and code examples focused on network maps, which is a more complex map type not previously covered. The new tutorial content below provides a a couple basic code examples for making network maps with mapmate.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>