<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Source Code on Matt&#39;s R Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/source-code/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Source Code on Matt&#39;s R Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Matthew Leonawicz</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/source-code/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Shiny app: Distributions of random variables</title>
      <link>/post/shiny-app-distributions-of-random-variables/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/shiny-app-distributions-of-random-variables/</guid>
      <description>There is a new version of my Distributions of Random Variables Shiny app available. This is a cleaned up modern revision of my original 2013 app series involving random variable probability distributions. The primary change is a switch to ggplot2 from base graphics. I have added this app to my shiny-apps GitHub repository so the source code is available, including a script containing all those pesky plotmath expressions.
The app draws and plots samples from various well known discrete and continuous probability distributions, all of which are available in base R with the single exception of the Pareto distribution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assorted Shiny apps collection, full code and data</title>
      <link>/post/2017-04-26-assorted-shiny-apps/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-04-26-assorted-shiny-apps/</guid>
      <description>Here is an assortment of R Shiny apps that you may find useful for exploration if you are in the process of learning Shiny and looking for something different. Some of these apps are very small and simple whereas others are large and complex. This repository provides full code and any necessary accompanying data sets. The repo also links to the apps hosted online at shinyapps.io so that you can run apps in your browser without having to download the entire collection repo to run apps locally.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Custom images for Shiny dashboard valueBox icons</title>
      <link>/post/custom-images-for-shiny-dashboard-valuebox-icons/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/custom-images-for-shiny-dashboard-valuebox-icons/</guid>
      <description>The shinydashboard package provides functions like valueBox that conveniently display basic information like summary statistics. In addition to presenting a value and subtitle on a colored background, an icon may be included as well. However, the icon must come from either the Font Awesome or Glyphicon icon libraries and cannot be image files.
I&amp;rsquo;ve provided a gist that shows how to achieve the use of custom icons with local image files stored in an app&amp;rsquo;s www/ directory.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>