<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Plots on Matthew Leonawicz | Blog: I think, therefore I R</title>
    <link>/tags/plots/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Plots on Matthew Leonawicz | Blog: I think, therefore I R</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Matthew Leonawicz</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/plots/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Mix ggplot2 graphs with your favorite memes. memery 0.4.2 released.</title>
      <link>/post/2018-02-09-mix-ggplot2-graphs-with-your-favorite-memes-memery-0-4-2-on-cran/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-02-09-mix-ggplot2-graphs-with-your-favorite-memes-memery-0-4-2-on-cran/</guid>
      <description>Make memorable plots with memery. memery is an R package that generates internet memes including superimposed inset graphs and other atypical features, combining the visual impact of an attention-grabbing meme with graphic results of data analysis. Version 0.4.2 of memery is now on CRAN. The latest development version and a package vignette are available on GitHub.
Changes in v0.4.2This latest version of memery includes a demo Shiny app.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Make memorable plots with memery. v0.3.0 now on CRAN.</title>
      <link>/post/2017-11-09-memery-0-3-0-on-cran/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-11-09-memery-0-3-0-on-cran/</guid>
      <description>Make memorable plots with memery. memery is an R package that generates internet memes including superimposed inset graphs and other atypical features, combining the visual impact of an attention-grabbing meme with graphic results of data analysis. Version 0.3.0 of memery is now on CRAN. The latest development version and a package vignette are available on GitHub.
Below is an example interleaving a semi-transparent ggplot2 graph between a meme image backdrop and overlying meme text labels.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>