<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Package on Matthew Leonawicz | Blog: I think, therefore I R</title>
    <link>/tags/package/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Package on Matthew Leonawicz | Blog: I think, therefore I R</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Matthew Leonawicz</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/package/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>My 2018 #rstats year in review</title>
      <link>/post/my-2018-rstats-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/my-2018-rstats-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>This past year in R has been a good one for me; productive, exciting, different. I decided it was worth taking a moment to reflect and share. Goals were set and met. There were also unexpected changes.
CRANA year ago, at the tail end of 2017, I published my first package to CRAN. It’s a fun, silly package, but I also had to make a successful case for in the initial review process to distinguish it from other similar works.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>epubr 0.5.0 CRAN release</title>
      <link>/post/epubr-0-5-0-cran-release/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/epubr-0-5-0-cran-release/</guid>
      <description>The epubr package provides functions supporting the reading and parsing of internal e-book content from EPUB files. This post briefly highlights the changes from v0.4.0. See the vignette for a more comprehensive introduction.
Minor additionThere is not much to see with the upgrade to version 0.5.0. Only one user function has been added, epub_cat. All this does is allow you to cat chunks of parsed e-book text to the console in a more readable manner.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>epubr 0.4.0 CRAN release</title>
      <link>/post/epubr-0-4-0-cran-release/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/epubr-0-4-0-cran-release/</guid>
      <description>The epubr package provides functions supporting the reading and parsing of internal e-book content from EPUB files. E-book metadata and text content are parsed separately and joined together in a tidy, nested tibble data frame.
E-book formatting is non-standard enough across all literature that no function can curate parsed e-book content across an arbitrary collection of e-books, in completely general form, resulting in a singular, consistently formatted output containing all the same variables.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>apputils 0.5.0 released</title>
      <link>/post/apputils-0-5-0-released/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/apputils-0-5-0-released/</guid>
      <description>Version 0.5.0 of the apputils R package has been released on GitHub. Complete documentation is available at the apputils website.
The key updates are:
 Added exApp for running Shiny app package examples. Ported custom icons demo app to apputils. Included all current custom icons in example app, adding the newer linear model themed icons. Added package css for infoBox override. Added introduction vignette content for stat boxes with package icons.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>