<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Shiny on Matthew Leonawicz | Blog: I think, therefore I R</title>
    <link>/tags/shiny/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Shiny on Matthew Leonawicz | Blog: I think, therefore I R</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Matthew Leonawicz</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/shiny/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>apputils 0.5.0 released</title>
      <link>/post/apputils-0-5-0-released/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/apputils-0-5-0-released/</guid>
      <description>Version 0.5.0 of the apputils R package has been released on GitHub. Complete documentation is available at the apputils website.
The key updates are:
 Added exApp for running Shiny app package examples. Ported custom icons demo app to apputils. Included all current custom icons in example app, adding the newer linear model themed icons. Added package css for infoBox override. Added introduction vignette content for stat boxes with package icons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate explorer update: monthly data and delta change</title>
      <link>/post/climate-explorer-update-monthly-data-and-delta-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/climate-explorer-update-monthly-data-and-delta-change/</guid>
      <description>The SNAP Climate Analytics Shiny app has been updated. Previously, the app included seasonally and annually aggregated data. With the recent inclusion of monthly data, the number of conditional spatio-temporal climate probability distributions has now increased from a base set of about 13 million unique distributions to over 46 million. The Season dropdown menu now offers annual average, 3-month seasonals, and individual months.
These conditional distributions for historical and projected temperature and precipitation over different geographic regions, time periods, climate models and greenhouse gas emissions scenarios represent the source data sets available in the app.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shiny app: Distributions of random variables</title>
      <link>/post/shiny-app-distributions-of-random-variables/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/shiny-app-distributions-of-random-variables/</guid>
      <description>There is a new version of my Distributions of Random Variables Shiny app available. This is a cleaned up modern revision of my original 2013 app series involving random variable probability distributions. The primary change is a switch to ggplot2 from base graphics. I have added this app to my shiny-apps GitHub repository so the source code is available, including a script containing all those pesky plotmath expressions.
The app draws and plots samples from various well known discrete and continuous probability distributions, all of which are available in base R with the single exception of the Pareto distribution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assorted Shiny apps collection, full code and data</title>
      <link>/post/2017-04-26-assorted-shiny-apps/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-04-26-assorted-shiny-apps/</guid>
      <description>Here is an assortment of R Shiny apps that you may find useful for exploration if you are in the process of learning Shiny and looking for something different. Some of these apps are very small and simple whereas others are large and complex. This repository provides full code and any necessary accompanying data sets. The repo also links to the apps hosted online at shinyapps.io so that you can run apps in your browser without having to download the entire collection repo to run apps locally.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Custom images for Shiny dashboard valueBox icons</title>
      <link>/post/custom-images-for-shiny-dashboard-valuebox-icons/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/custom-images-for-shiny-dashboard-valuebox-icons/</guid>
      <description>The shinydashboard package provides functions like valueBox that conveniently display basic information like summary statistics. In addition to presenting a value and subtitle on a colored background, an icon may be included as well. However, the icon must come from either the Font Awesome or Glyphicon icon libraries and cannot be image files.
I&amp;rsquo;ve provided a gist that shows how to achieve the use of custom icons with local image files stored in an app&amp;rsquo;s www/ directory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R animation: global SNAP Shiny app users</title>
      <link>/post/r-animation-global-snap-shiny-app-users/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/r-animation-global-snap-shiny-app-users/</guid>
      <description>For the blog readers, just a quick heads up that I have posted a new R data animation to YouTube. A complete post will follow, but for now here is the video. It displays the social network of SNAP Shiny app users over about the past year and a half using great circle trajectories on a rotating 3D Earth. It&amp;rsquo;s best in 1080p, but still somewhat degraded for streaming. I&amp;rsquo;ll post the raw source video later as well, which is crystal clear.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>