<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tabs on Matthew Leonawicz | Blog: I think, therefore I R</title>
    <link>/tags/tabs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tabs on Matthew Leonawicz | Blog: I think, therefore I R</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Matthew Leonawicz</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/tabs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>tabr 0.3.0 on CRAN</title>
      <link>/post/tabr-0-3-0-on-cran/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tabr-0-3-0-on-cran/</guid>
      <description>The tabr package for creating guitar tablature (&amp;ldquo;tabs&amp;rdquo;) from R code is now available on CRAN. tabr provides programmatic music notation and a wrapper around LilyPond for creating quality guitar tablature.
This post is just a quick update to mention that v0.3.0 has now been released on CRAN. And since I don&amp;rsquo;t have much time for blogging, I&amp;rsquo;m basically just pasting the release notes here below.
But the key changes are these:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>tabr package for guitar tablature now on CRAN</title>
      <link>/post/tabr-package-for-guitar-tablature-now-on-cran/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tabr-package-for-guitar-tablature-now-on-cran/</guid>
      <description>The tabr package for creating guitar tablature (&amp;ldquo;tabs&amp;rdquo;) from R code is now available on CRAN. tabr provides programmatic music notation and a wrapper around LilyPond for creating quality guitar tablature.
tabr offers functions for describing and organizing musical structures and wraps around the LilyPond backend. LilyPond is an open source music engraving program for generating high quality sheet music based on markup syntax. tabr generates files following the LilyPond markup syntax to be subsequently processed by LilyPond into sheet music.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing tabr: guitar tabs with R</title>
      <link>/post/introducing-tabr-guitar-tabs-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/introducing-tabr-guitar-tabs-with-r/</guid>
      <description>This post introduces a new R package I am working on called tabr for creating guitar tablature (&amp;ldquo;tabs&amp;rdquo;) from R code. The tabr package provides programmatic music notation and a wrapper around LilyPond for creating quality guitar tablature.
tabr offers functions for describing and organizing musical structures and wraps around the LilyPond backend. LilyPond is an open source music engraving program for generating high quality sheet music based on markup syntax.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>