<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Statistics on Matthew Leonawicz | Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/statistics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Statistics on Matthew Leonawicz | Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Matthew Leonawicz</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/statistics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>apputils 0.5.0 released</title>
      <link>/post/apputils-0-5-0-released/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/apputils-0-5-0-released/</guid>
      <description>Version 0.5.0 of the apputils R package has been released on GitHub. Complete documentation is available at the apputils website.
The key updates are:
 Added exApp for running Shiny app package examples. Ported custom icons demo app to apputils. Included all current custom icons in example app, adding the newer linear model themed icons. Added package css for infoBox override. Added introduction vignette content for stat boxes with package icons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate explorer update: monthly data and delta change</title>
      <link>/post/climate-explorer-update-monthly-data-and-delta-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/climate-explorer-update-monthly-data-and-delta-change/</guid>
      <description>The SNAP Climate Analytics Shiny app has been updated. Previously, the app included seasonally and annually aggregated data. With the recent inclusion of monthly data, the number of conditional spatio-temporal climate probability distributions has now increased from a base set of about 13 million unique distributions to over 46 million. The Season dropdown menu now offers annual average, 3-month seasonals, and individual months.
These conditional distributions for historical and projected temperature and precipitation over different geographic regions, time periods, climate models and greenhouse gas emissions scenarios represent the source data sets available in the app.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>mapmate 0.2.0</title>
      <link>/post/mapmate-0-2-0/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/mapmate-0-2-0/</guid>
      <description>mapmate is under development and blog posts can become outdated quickly. Up to date mapmate documentation and tutorial examples can be found at the official mapmate Github pages.
mapmate has now been updating from version 0.1.0 to 0.2.0 on Github. The key change is the incorporation of new functions, help docs and code examples focused on network maps, which is a more complex map type not previously covered. The new tutorial content below provides a a couple basic code examples for making network maps with mapmate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R animation: great circles 3, final draft</title>
      <link>/post/r-animation-great-circles-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/r-animation-great-circles-3/</guid>
      <description>Here is the final draft of my great circle arcs R animation. I made this back in January shortly after my first two drafts, but am only now getting around to sharing it, which is a typical representation of how seldom I can make time for blogging. But given the recent spike in interest (thanks to Urban Demographics for sharing my work) in the first, and roughest, draft, I am motivated to finally share something better.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>